<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Discourse concerning the grounds &amp; causes of this miserable civill war wherein Ireland is exhausted, England wasted, and Scotland likely to be imbroyled, and wherein not only liberty but religion is endangered, &amp;c.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1644</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 93 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A36088</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D1587</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R15277</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12543021</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12543021</idno>
            <idno type="VID">63000</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A36088)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 63000)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 313:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Discourse concerning the grounds &amp; causes of this miserable civill war wherein Ireland is exhausted, England wasted, and Scotland likely to be imbroyled, and wherein not only liberty but religion is endangered, &amp;c.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1644?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Date of publication from NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:63000:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A DISCOVRSE CONCERNING THE GROVNDS &amp; CAVSES of this miſerable civill war; Wherein <hi>Ireland</hi> is exhauſted, <hi>England</hi> waſted, and <hi>Scotland</hi> likely to be imbroyled: and wherein not only Liberty, but Religion is endangered, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">K</seg>ING CHARLES was within few late yeeres, quietly poſſeſt of three flouriſhing Kingdomes; and for a while, as his ſubjects ſeerned to enjoy all the blandiſhments of peace under his raigne, to the envie of other Nations; ſo hee appear'd eminently glorious in the inviolable loyalty and obedience of his ſubjects; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o the inciting of envie amongſt other Princes.</p>
            <p>But to that ſerene, delightfull calme; a moſt diſmall tempeſt hath ſince ſucceeded; and in ſo ſhort a traverſe of time a more wofull, deſperate Cataſtrophe (then this which now confounds: both King and ſubjects) was ſcarce ever brought about in any other Country. All our gameſome Holidayes paſt, ſeeme now to us like the ſleepe of <hi>Ionah</hi> in the ſhip, the trance thereof on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly lockt up our ſenſes for a while, that we might be betrayed to the greater horror and amazement, when the incurſion of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expected ralamities ſhould immediatly ſeize us under ſo dead and ſtupid a condition. <hi>Ireland</hi> already is become as ſad a
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:63000:2"/>ſpectacle as the ruthleſſe hand of war ever made any ſince <hi>Veſpaſians</hi> dayes: and <hi>England,</hi> though it ſinkes a little more ſlowly, yet is in the poſture of ſinking, and is not to be ſuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted but by a divine hand more then ordinary: and laſtly, <hi>Scotland</hi> is but one degree onely more removed from deſtruction. The greater the Popiſh faction is in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and the more potent that Court-party there is, which ſuggeſts to it ſelfe probable advantages out of the ſhipwrack of broken <hi>England,</hi> the more inevitably is that Nation owned and deſtin'd to the ſame ruine as <hi>England;</hi> let not dreames infatuate, ſhe muſt expect the ſame line to be ſtretched over her, as <hi>England</hi> has, if ſhe prevent not her fate by ſome ſiſterly aſſiſtance, whileſt it is thus diſtant, ſhe ſhall certainly unpitied periſh at its neerer approach.</p>
            <p>But the Queſtion is, Whence did theſe unnaturall broyles ſpring and ariſe; Hath the Kings miſgovernment, or the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions rebellious diſpoſition, cauſed theſe ſudden diſtempers? has all this diſcord beene ſtirr'd principally by Eccleſiaſticall or Civill Perſons? and have their ends been temporall or ſpirituall? How does that commotion which was in <hi>Scotland</hi> differ in cauſe from ours in <hi>England;</hi> or this in <hi>England</hi> from that in <hi>Ireland?</hi> Has it beene the ſame deſigne carryed on for many yeeres together, from whoſe maturity at length all our troubles in all the three Nations have been derived? Or have the <hi>Scots</hi> occaſionally aimed at one thing, the <hi>Iriſh</hi> at another, and the <hi>Engliſh</hi> at another? If the Rebels in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the Parliament in <hi>England</hi> have purpoſes diametrically oppoſite, how is it that the King proteſts againſt both? how comes it, that he wages a war upon the Parliament, that is as favourable to the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> as deſtructive to the <hi>Engliſh?</hi> And if the <hi>Scots</hi> and the <hi>Engliſh</hi> propoſe the ſame thing, how is it that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> are thus implacably Proſecured, whileſt the <hi>Scots</hi> are friendly intreated? How is it, that Papiſts are ſo far united, yea, even in <hi>Ireland</hi> where they pretend for the King, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the acknowledgement of our Court, yet all of them move undevided, and in <hi>England,</hi> where they fight for the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:63000:2"/>King, and are accordingly entertained and allowed ſo to doe; yet ſtill they are unanimous, whereas Proteſtants hold no per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect correſpondence any where, in <hi>Ireland</hi> they joyne againſt Papiſts, yet favour the Papiſts cauſe in <hi>England;</hi> and in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> they fight under Popiſh Banners, and by conſequence maintaine the <hi>Romiſh</hi> faith, both in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland?</hi> And if theſe miſeries have beene not meere late accidentall events, but the ſtudyed and prepared accompliſhments and producti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of divers former yeeres, then whether is't more probable, that the Parliament, hath beene this long time buſie in plotting againſt the Court, or the Court againſt the Parliament?</p>
            <p>To give ſatisfaction to all men in all theſe Queeries, will be difficult; but to give ſatisfaction to all honeſt Proteſtants, and to convince all our moſt ſubtill enemies, be they Proteſtants or Papiſts, will not be impoſſible; and therefore my utmoſt skill ſhal endevour it. And if this age will not give me credit therein, I am certaine the next will; I will commandingly ſay, That it ſhall without diſſent and deniall receive and acknowledge theſe truths which I now deliver.</p>
            <p>The ſonnes of the <hi>Iewes</hi> erected Trophyes, and built Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of honour for thoſe Prophets which had been ſtoned in the ages before, and yet at the ſame time, perhaps they mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly murdered the true ſucceſſors of the ſame Prophets; ſuch difference is there betwixt the evidence of preſent and paſt truth; nevertheleſſe, I ſhall for the preſent lye the leſſe obnoxious to contradiction or diſtruſt, becauſe I ſhall not ſo much inſiſt upon conjectures or nude averments of my owne, as the cenſures of ſtrangers and Papiſts; and the judgements of other Stateſmen, whoſe partiality herein is the leſſe to be ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected.</p>
            <p>The great tyranie and uſurpation of <hi>Roman</hi> Prelates, who (to purchaſe to themſelves an Eccleſiaſticall Empire, more large and uncontroleable then any temporall Monarch ever challenged) had perverted Religion and innovated the whole frame of Chriſtianity; began to be diſcovered to many in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:63000:3"/>about 120 yeeres ſince: <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth alſo, ſo farre as his owne Crowne was concerned therein, was willing to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance the diſcovery; but as for a totall reformation of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, or redemption of his ſubjects liberty from popiſh thral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, no ſuch thought ever entred into his breaſt. 'Twas in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different to him on the ſame day, and in the ſame place, to hang a Papiſt maintaining the Popes ſupremacy, and to burne a Proteſtant denying thoſe corruptions of Religion whereupon that ſupemacy was founded: ſo indigeſted and rude a Chaos of Doctrine was that which he ſought to authoriſe and to daub over with his untempered morter. <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixth, by a more bleſſed illumination, ſet himſelfe to pull downe the whole fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bricke, and to raze the very foundation of Hierarchy; and had it not been a worke of more yeeres, then it pleaſed God to adde to his life, hee ſurely had not left one ſtone upon another. Queen <hi>Mary</hi> ſet her ſelfe as entirely to repaire the Popes Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, as her brother did to ruine it; yea, even to the effuſion of much blood, with a more fierce zeale ſhe laboured in it, and had not death overtaken her, and the hand of God otherwiſe croſſed her, perhaps no hopes had been left for a new reſtau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration under her ſucceſſor. Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> with as perfect an integrity as either her brothers was in maintenance of truth, or her ſiſters in maintenance of ſuperſtition, applyed her ſelfe and her utmoſt power to reſtore Religion againe in full con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity to her brother, and oppoſition to her ſiſter.</p>
            <p>Two admirable Councellors ſhe had, <hi>Cecyll</hi> and <hi>Bacon,</hi> both cordiall and totally addicted to the Proteſtant Religion: the honour of whom leaves her honour unqueſtionable; for as much as to chooſe good inſtruments is the nobleſt teſtimony of goodneſſe: and the influence of Princes upon ſervants, is greater then that of ſervants upon Princes. I have heard that the then Earle of <hi>Pembrooke</hi> being ſollicited by other Court Grandees, to erter into a confederacie with them about ſome alteration in Church and State, he told them plainly, he durſt not venture his manner of <hi>Wilton</hi> in the buſineſſe, unleſſe <hi>Cecyll</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:63000:3"/>and <hi>Bacon</hi> were firſt hanged at the Court gate; and to hang them would be a matter not to be compaſſed, till they with their Rhetoricke in <hi>Cheapſide</hi> ſhould avert the Citizens hearts from them, and that he left as a fond conceit. Nevertheleſſe, in cenſure of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> ſome have ſaid that ſhe ſwept the roome cleane, but yet left all the duſt heaped up behind the doore, and did not carry it forth as ſhe ought to have done. Their meaning, I conceive, is, that though ſhe much awed and reſtrained both Prelates and Papiſts, ſo as they durſt not at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt any thing againſt the conſtitution of this State, during her raigne; yet ſhe left them not in ſo deſperate a condition, but that they did recover ſtrength, and reunite againe after her death. This cenſure ſeemes to me too harſh: for Prelates without the copulation of Papiſts to gender a filthy ſpawne upon them, are not of any conſiderable danger; and Papiſts by her long and proſperous raigne, were as much quelled and diſabled, as poſſible they could be. If any duſt was left behind the doore, 'twas becauſe her life-time was not extenſive enough for the carrying it forth; forthe reduction of <hi>Ireland</hi> was very late, ſhee ſcarce ſurvived it, and yet to make the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, was of farre more difficultie, and would conſume longer time then to make them ſubjects.</p>
            <p>The propogation of the true Faith therefore in <hi>Ireland,</hi> was a taske which Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> was of neceſſity to leave to her ſucceſſors; and 'tis very probable, had they begun where ſhee deſiſted, and not deviated from her reſolution, that Kingdome had long ere this, afforded as many Proteſtants as ſubjects; whereas now it denyes both: for doubtleſſe Q. <hi>Elizabeth</hi> at her deceaſe, left <hi>Ireland</hi> in better diſpoſition to conforme to <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> then ſhe found <hi>England</hi> in at her ſiſters deceaſe to revolt from <hi>Rome,</hi> and therefore with the ſame induſtry her ſucceſſors might have done the ſame in <hi>Ireland</hi> as ſhe had done in <hi>England.</hi> But alas, no ſuch courſe was take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there, we have reaſon to think rather that Popery was cheriſhed and preſerv'd in <hi>Ireland,</hi> to make way for theſe tragicall diviſions, then that there was any
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:63000:4"/>deſigne or undertaking to plant <hi>Proteſtantiſme</hi> in it, for the eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhing further union between the nations: The example of Q. <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> to whom the protection of God was as conſtant in ſaving her from the bloody Emiſſaries of <hi>Rome,</hi> did not work ſo ſtrongly to animate King <hi>Iames:</hi> as the Apoſtacie of <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>French</hi> King, whom God deſerted for his deſertion, did ſerve to intimidate him. The revolt of <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, who gained the Title of Great by his warlike atchievements, and the horrible conjuration of the Powder Traytors here in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> made ſo ſtrong impreſſion upon the ſoft and mild temper of King <hi>Iames;</hi> that to temporiſe a little with <hi>Rome,</hi> for better ſecurity of his Perſon, appeared at that time very ſeaſonable; wherefore to dally with Antichriſt a little, letters were written to Cardinall <hi>Perrone,</hi> and anſwers received about a reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Religions, and in order thereunto, the rigour of penall lawes was rebated; nay, countenance was ſhewed to Papiſts, the grandour of Prelates and pompe of Ceremonies in the Church began to be affected. The neerer alſo that King <hi>Iames</hi> his end approached, the more it reſembled <hi>Salomons,</hi> and grew tainted with the foule ſymptomes of a declination; in ſo much that ſcarce any but Papiſts were admitted to governe his Councels, and then the whole Kingdome began to be expoſed as a prey, to <hi>Spaniſh, French, Italian</hi> penſioners. It was well obſerved by the Duke of <hi>Roan</hi> that no Prince in <hi>Europe</hi> ſo much oppoſed his owne intereſts, both in civill and religious affaires as King <hi>Iames;</hi> for, doubtleſſe the Pope by his agents in all Church matters, was more potent then the King himſelfe; and ſo was <hi>Gundamore</hi> in matters of State, had not the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Duch,</hi> and ſome other Nations interfered with the Pope and <hi>Spantard,</hi> and given gold for ſome part in us rather to ſave us, then that we ſhould be loſt to their enemies; doubtleſſe we had been diſpoſed of quickly; our happineſſe was, that <hi>France</hi> was liberall enough to buy us from <hi>Spain,</hi> and <hi>Spain</hi> liberall enough to buy us from <hi>France, &amp;c.</hi> though our miſery was, that both ſides pulled away more from us, then they parted withall from
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:63000:4"/>themſelves. And now when three Kingdomes are under the ſubjection of one Prince, who is under the ſubjection of one luſtfull, raſh, young Favourite, and that Favourite ſolely at the devotion of his vitious, opprobrious, miſchievous mother, and that mother a meere Votareſſe to Rome, utterly forfeited, reſigned, and ſold to the commands of Jeſuites: When our miſerable Nations are in this ridiculous, prepoſterous poſture of government, who can wonder that a Spaniſh or French Match for our Prince ſhould be deſigned? As great a maſſe of treaſure might have been received with a German Lady, and that with leſſe expence (for the portion of Spaine or France can ſcarſe equall the charge of fetching it) all that can be ſaid is, Piſtols and Patachoons are more valuable than Dollars, in our judgement. Alliance alſo amongſt Princes, if it be of any, it is of dangerous conſequence, it is certaine to produce reall enmitie and emulation: but it is uncertaine to produce ſo much as a ſhadow of amitie and union, eſpecially amongſt Princes of the Romiſh Religion. If we negotiate concerning a marriage with the Spaniſh <hi>Infanta,</hi> 'tis neceſſarie that wee keep faire intelligence with France, and capitulate ſtrongly with the German Princes: and if wee break off with Spaine, and treat with the French Lady, 'tis neceſſarie that wee enter into a new confederacie with Spaine, and prepare a Fleet for the Iſle of Rhees. So much weaker than cobwebs are the bonds of matrimony amongſt ambitious Monarchs.</p>
            <p>Something alſo may be ſaid againſt the inceſtuous extracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Houſe of Auſtria, and the Florentine mixtures of the Houſe of Burbon; whereas the nobilitie, chaſtitie, and beautie of the German Dames, hath ever been not only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all exception, but alſo beyond all compariſon. Nothing then but Poperie (unleſſe wee will add alſo the manifold mif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefes of Poperie) could be aimed at in a Popiſh Alliance by thoſe devilliſh Engineers, which were the inſolent Lords of our Lords, or rather of our Lords, Lords, Lords.</p>
            <p>And if we deſire further ſatisfaction therein, let us conſider
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:63000:5"/>the ſubſtance of the Popes letter written the 20 of April, 1623. to our Prince in Spaine, and our Princes Anſwer there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, as they are faithfully tranſlated, and regiſtred by <hi>Du Cheſne</hi> the French Geographer, in his Book, fol. 1162.</p>
            <p>The Popes Rhetorick in briefe flowes thus:</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>MOſt noble Prince: the former Kings of Britain have been very famous for their devotion to the Popes Chaire, and now though the ſtate of the Engliſh Church be altered, yet the Court is adorned with ſuch morall vertues, as may ſupport our charitie; and the more the glorie of your moſt clement Father, and the reſentment of your royall nature (or inclination) delights us, the more ardour there is in us, to open the gates of Heaven to you. We commend your deſigne, which hath directed you to take a journey into Spaine, to allye your ſelfe to the Houſe of Auſtria, it elevates us to the hope of extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie advantage; our open teſtimony is in this preſent affaire, that you are he which has the principall care and regard of our Prelacie: for ſince you deſire to take in marriage a daughter of Spaine, we ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily conjecture that your Progenitours Zeale may againe revive in your ſoule; and its not credible, that hee that loves ſuch alliance ſhould hate the Catholike Religion, or take delight in oppreſsing the holy Seat. Therefore publike interceſsion is made continually by our command, that you may be put into poſſeſsion of that moſt noble heri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, which your Anceſtours have purchaſed for you, to defend the authoritie of the Soveraigne Biſhop, and to combat againſt the mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of hereſie. The moſt ſacred Kings of England came formerly from England to Rome accompanied with Angels, to honour and doe homage to the Prince of the Apoſtles in his Chaire Apoſtolicall: let their actions be as ſo many voyces of God, to exhort you to the ſame, and to bring you back againe into the lap of the Romane Church. Their ſighs and groanes are anceſſant for your ſalvation, and you cannot give greater conſolation to Chriſtendome, than to put the Prince of the Apoſtles into poſſeſsion of your moſt noble Iſle, holding his authoritie as the defence of your Kengdomes, and as a Divine Oracle. Our great charitie makes us deſire, that you and your royall
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:63000:5"/>Father may be enobled with the names of Deliverers and Reſtau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratours of the ancient paternall Religion of Britaine: and the care of our charitie in this is no other, than to procure your happineſſe.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>The Anſwer in ſhort is thus couched.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>Moſt holy Father: I received your Sanctities diſpatch with grand contentment, and with a reſpect beſeeming the pietie and benevolence thereof. I have read the Elogies of my Royall Progeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours, who have expoſed their eſtates and lives for the exaltation of the holy Chaire, (ſet before mine eyes by your Holineſſe for imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) with pleaſure unexpreſsible, and as juſtly deſerved by them. Neither was their courage againſt the enemies of the Croſſe leſſe, than the thought and care which I have to unite all Chriſtian Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: nor doe I eſteeme it a greater honour to be deſcended of ſo great Princes, than to repreſent them in the Zeale of their pietie. The knowledge which I have of my moſt honour'd Fathers mind, and the concurrence of his Catholike Majeſtie, to whom the preſent divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of Chriſtian Princes is ſo grievous; and the fore-ſight of your Holineſſe, who judged this marriage with the <hi>Infanta</hi> of Spaine ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie for procuring of publike union, and therefore deſigned it, are great encouragements to me. Wherefore 'tis moſt certaine, I ſhall never be ſo extremely affectionate to any thing in the world, as to ſeek alliance with a Prince that hath the ſame ſenſe of true Religion with my ſelfe. I have been alwayes verie far from encouraging no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velties, or being a partie in any faction againſt the Catholike, Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolike, Roman Religion: but have ſought all occaſions to remove ſuch ſuſpitions from reſting on me. And for the future, ſince wee all beleeve in one Ieſus Christ, I will ſtraine all my power to have but one religion and one faith; and I am reſolved to ſpare nothing in the world, but to ſuffer all manner of diſcommodities, even to the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard of life and eſtate, for the effecting hereof. It reſts only, that I thank your Holineſſe for your permiſsion and accord herein; and I pray God to bleſſe you, for the great travaile which your Holineſſe hath ſuſtained in his Church.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:63000:6"/>
            <p>If this was Court-diſſimulation, Gods name was too far uſed in it, and the diſſimulation has extended further than to language; the maine affaires of our Court and Church, for many yeares together, have been conformable to the ſame ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions. And if here was plaine meaning without diſſimula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, no words of man can more fully and clearly juſtifie Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perie, and proteſt againſt the novelties and hereſies of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches than theſe do. And the Pope, it ſeemes, ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected no diſſimulation herein, nor his Councellours, and principall Miniſters, (and yet they are not uſually gulled, or blinded, or out-done in that kind of Craft) and for proofe hereof, I will inſtance in Father <hi>Iohn de Monte-Major</hi> of the Societie of <hi>Ieſus,</hi> and I will be verie briefe herein, and confine my ſelfe only to him. This Jeſuite was a ſubtile Stateſ-man (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s we may perceive by his arguments now in print) and in the <hi>Iunto</hi> at Madrid, when the marriage of the <hi>Infanta</hi> with our Prince was upon debate, for anſwer to ſuch difficulties and objections as ſome other of the <hi>Iunto</hi> had offered to oppoſe the marriage, he divers times inſiſted upon ſuch points as theſe: <hi>Since the Prince is a man ſettled in his manners, and makes great ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of our holy Law, it may with ſufficient probabilitie be heped, that by the good example of the moſt illuſtrious</hi> Infanta, <hi>and all her Attendants, both men and women, and by the holineſſe and doctrine of her Confeſſour, he will be eaſily brought to our holy faith.</hi> fol. 6. a. <hi>And therefore as we have ſeene that the Prince and his father have kept their agreement made at the Treatie of peace, for the well uſing of Catholikes; and we are informed out of England, that this yeare in the holy week within London, there have been at the Communion</hi> 4000 <hi>Catholikes in the Embaſſadours houſe, and that they have made</hi> 40 <hi>monuments, no body ſpeaking one word to controll them:</hi> fol. 7. a. <hi>Both the Prince and his father doe extremely deſire the friendſhip of his Holineſſe, and of Spaine, which</hi> Henry <hi>the eighth little did care for: and that's the reaſon which moveth the Prince and his father to procure this marriage, is to eſtabliſh the ſaid fried<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with the Apoſtolike See, and the Crowne of Spaine,</hi> fol. 7. b.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:63000:6"/>
               <hi>Another principall thing to be obſerved is, that the Prince (at all other Engliſh and French Hereticks doe) beleeve that we are ſaved, keeping the religion of the Church of Rome.</hi> fol. 8. b. <hi>There are ſufficient ſignes ſhewing that the King of England is well affected to our Religion, ſince it appeares hee with ſuch care and paines endevours to match his ſon with a ſpouſe ſo much Catholike, daughter to ſo Catholike Parents, and hee being the only Heire of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, againſt the advice of all the Hereticks, and all his Councel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, and all the enemies of this Crowne, hath ſent him with great danger of his health and life, &amp;c. All which is a great ſigne, that hee being moved with ſome great light from Heaven, deſires to forſake the new Religion he profeſſeth, and to returne to the old one profeſſed by his Predeceſſours, for ſo many ages. The Prince gives cleare te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony to be well affected to our holy Law, ſince hee beleeveth, and hath ſpoken it to divers perſons, that thoſe that follow the ſame are ſaved in it, &amp;c. being Grand-child to a Grand-mother that dyed a Martyr.</hi> fol. 9. a. <hi>Thus great hope may be, that the whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome ſhall be reduced to the Catholike Faith.</hi> fol. 9. b. <hi>It is to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted how earneſtly this match hath been purſued and treated for, both with his Holineſſe and other perſons, debated in many</hi> Junto's <hi>by moſt learned men.</hi> fol. 10. b. <hi>There ſhall be kept a publike Church in London for the Catholikes, a Biſhop of that Citie, libertie of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, the children ſhall be brought up by their mother</hi> (<hi>the</hi> Infanta) <hi>till they be fourteene yeares of age, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where ſuch great Agents of the Hierarchy have not only delivered their judgements ſo plainly, but alſo ſet forth the reaſons whereupon their judgements are grounded ſo clearly, I ſhall forbeare any further to deliver mine. Theſe things are publike enough in the Spaniſh tongue. But let us ſtay no more upon times ſo long agoe elapſed, let us for brevitie ſake omit all diſcourſe concerning the wars in Bohemia, the Palati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, Rochell, and other countries, where our falſe promiſes of ſupplyes and aids, purpoſely (as is thought) deſtroyed the Proteſtant cauſe; let us now lightly paſſe over the former part of theſe laſt twentie yeares, and chiefly fix our diſcourſe
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:63000:7"/>upon the alterations and innovations of the latter part therof. Whilſt the Queene was verie young, and the plot of our Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarchiſts not fully ripe, the Babyloniſh Myſteries were not fit to be revealed: and yet even in thoſe times, the work went on darkly and inſenſibly, and ſome uſe was made of the verie looſneſſe and exceſſe of thoſe times, to help on the perfection thereof.</p>
            <p>This violent ſharp malady, of which we labour ſo diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedly at this preſent, began to ſeize the vitals of this State, long before its violence appeared, and the venome thereof, as if it were of affinitie with that of the <hi>Tarantula,</hi> whilſt it was in its ſlow growth, cauſed rather fits of jollitie, than pangs of dolour in us. That which is now murther, rapine, lamentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, was within theſe twentie yeeres masking, triumphing, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velling; ſo that hee that writes the ſtorie of our overthrow, muſt ſay that we drunk, and danced, and ſported our ſelves to death: ſome mortall and noxious potions may yet be delicate to the palate, and others of medicinall and ſalubrious vertue may offend the taſte verie much: ſo it is with times, ſome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounding in diſſolute merriment, may yet conduce to a Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons overthrow, whilſt others more ſad and uncouth may be helpfull towards a recoverie. 'Tis not juſt therefore in the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of Parliaments, to aſcribe the cauſe of our preſent miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries to the Parliament, or to exclaime againſt theſe times for being as yet miſerable: neither ought they ſo much to boaſt of that falſe betraying jollitie, which we ſeemed heretofore to enjoy. 'Tis now about ten yeares ſince a <hi>Nuntio</hi> came over from the Pope, the buſineſſe before was tranſacted by Sir <hi>Toby Mathewes,</hi> and ſome other more privie Inſtruments; for we muſt not think that a <hi>Nuntio</hi> was ſent, till his way was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore made, and entertainment agreed upon, and that agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment alſo (we muſt needs think) had its preparations, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious conſiderations: but to limit our diſcourſe to theſe laſt ten yeares, and to give a verie briefe account of them, from the mouth of ſuch as are not partiall, let us in the firſt place make
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:63000:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>uſe of that Cenſure and Narrative which hath beene lately publiſhed in Print, and is entituled, <hi>The Popes Nuntio,</hi> &amp;c. The Authour of that Diſcourſe, was a <hi>Venetian,</hi> and ſeemes a man equally ingenuous and obſerving, and becauſe he was a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt, we may not think he did utter any untruth to the diſadvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of his own religion; and becauſe he was imploy'd in ſtate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matters at Court, we may gheſſe that what he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municated was for the moſt part of things within his owne knowledge and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity; the piece alſo is faithfully tranſlated out of the Italian and French, and was valued and preferred as a thing not fit for vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar eyes by great Stateſmen of other Nations; and there are few of our owne Nation and Religion that had any ſight into Court affaires, but they know well, much more might have been ſaid, and is likely yet to be diſcovered. However by the light of that Pamphlet, we ſhall be informed, that the word Popery is of various ambiguous ſignification; ſo that he which abjures the Romiſh Religion, may yet like well of a reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with <hi>Rome.</hi> And Reconciliation in the next place, is a thing that may admit of ſuch and ſuch degrees and ſteps both of one ſide and the other, and ſuch fraud may be uſed in a Treaty of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation, that one ſide may condeſcend to more then is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, and the other gaine more then is pretended; and in all theſe points, our <hi>Venetian,</hi> if he be rightly and throughly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, will ſatisfie our doubts, and cleare our ambiguities; I ſhall deſire therefore all impartiall diſ-ingaged men, to review our <hi>Venetians</hi> diſcourſe with me, and to give me leave to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcant thereupon a little, whileſt I fetch my conſiderations no higher nor further than the method and guidance of that Pamphlet directs me: our <hi>Venetian</hi> tells us, that King <hi>Charles</hi> once was heard to ſay, that Hee could at that time reconcile himſelfe to the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> with much advantage: for our better information therein, and that wee may neither miſtake the Kings intention, nor conceale our owne danger, let us make uſe of our <hi>Venetians</hi> diſcourſe in theſe five particulars:</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:63000:8"/>
            <list>
               <item>1 Let us from hence learne to underſtand what the reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation was; and how far each ſide ſhould comply and ſubmit according to the capitulation.</item>
               <item>2 Who were the parties to be reconciled.</item>
               <item>3 What were the expedients and meanes of effecting or ſpeeding this reconciliation.</item>
               <item>4 What that profit and great advantage was, which the King promiſed to himſelfe by this reconciliation.</item>
               <item>5 What the difficulties and obſtacles were which did retard this reconciliation.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1 We ſhall do well, firſt to take into our conſideration the articles and capitulation betwixt both parties, whereby it was agreed how far the Papiſts ſhould meete the Proteſtants, and how far the Proteſtants ſhould advance towards the Papiſts; the Pope was to move towards us but very ſlowly, in a pace ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding majeſticall; his Holineſſe was pleaſed, not without much difficulty to diſpence with foure things: Firſt, that mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage might be permitted to Prieſts: Secondly, that the oath of allegeance and ſupremacie, ſo far as it concerned the Kings temporall power, with ſome mild interpretations or alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons might be tollerated for his Majeſties ſecurity: Thirdly, that the Communion might be adminiſtred <hi>ſub utraque ſpecie:</hi> Fourthly, that the Lyturgie might be officiated in the Engliſh tongue. Theſe two laſt articles were for the ſatisfaction of the people. 'Twas the great zeale of <hi>Canterbury</hi> to capitulate for theſe things, to make the entrance of Popery the more ſmooth at firſt; and this was about the latter end of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> or the begining of <hi>September,</hi> 1636. during the reſidence of Seig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nior <hi>Con;</hi> and though our <hi>Venetian</hi> help us not herein, yet this is knowne ſufficiently, and can be averred otherwiſe; neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, we may probably conjecture, that what did concerne the King herein, ſhould have been really performed, ſo far forth as other Catholike Princes uſually injoy, and expect as their due; and ſo far as the Biſhops were to be independent both from King and Pope (which was the maine ſcope and purpoſe
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:63000:8"/>of the agreement, though not mentioned at all in the articles) there was no feare of breach on the Popes part, but ſo far as the inferiour Clergie, and the people were concerned, the after performance (it is to be ſuſpected) was to be left to the Popes diſcretion, the conditions being onely of temporall advantage, rather fit to induce than to confirme Popery. This ſeemes the more likely to be true, becauſe of the great facility which was in our Divines to comply with the Papiſts of their owne accord without any allurements, or follicitation at all; the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts were not ſo backward in walking towards <hi>Calvin,</hi> as the Proteſtants were haſty in running towards the Pope; for even before any Treaty at all, or before any Nuntio ſent from <hi>Rome,</hi> we had condeſcended to many popiſh innovations, and altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, both in doctrine and diſcipline; and 'twas at our intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that any Nuntio was diſpatched at all. It is not worth while to reckon up here, what novelties had been patronized, and by whom, how far <hi>Sparrow</hi> had paved the way for auricular confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, <hi>Watts</hi> for penance, <hi>Heylin</hi> for altar-worſhip, <hi>Mountague</hi> for Saint-worſhip, <hi>Laud</hi> for the Maſſe, and many others; it is not worth while to recite, how far the ſanctity of the Sabbath was depraved, and all ſtrictneſſe of life under the ſcandall of Puritaniſme diſparaged, or how far Arminianiſme, Socini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aniſme, Atheiſme it ſelfe was countenanced, the eaſier to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boſh the Clergie, and people, and to prepare them for altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of any kind, it having beene obſerved; <hi>that to ſome men irreligion it ſelfe ſeemed leſſe offenſive than the Popiſh Religion: our Venetians owne words are; The Vniverſities, Biſhops and Divines of this Realme, doe daily imbrace Catholike opinions, though they profeſſe it not with open mouth, for feare of the Puritanes: for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, they hold that the Church of Rome is a true Church; that the Pope is ſuperiour to all Biſhops; that to him it appertaines to call generall Councels; that it is lawfull to pray for the ſoules departeds; that Altars ought to be erected; in ſumme, they believe all that is taught by the Church, but not by the Court of Rome.</hi> In another place he reports <hi>the King to be much a favourer of Confeſsion,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:63000:9"/>and ſayes, that by his countenance, Catholikes did increaſe daily.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At the Councell of <hi>Trent</hi> all matters concerning the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> which are of themſelves but diſputable, were deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined and enjoyned as points of faith to be believed upon ſtrict paine of damnation; but matters of faith indeed, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> were left diſputable, and no <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thema</hi> annexed to them. Now, the Court of <hi>England</hi> having contrary intereſts in this reſpect, was not ſo far Popiſh, and therefore <hi>Canterbury</hi> himſelfe would ever profeſſe againſt theſe <hi>Tridentine</hi> Papiſts, whom onely he hated as Papiſts properly ſo called. Nevertheleſſe, we muſt not conceive, that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Laytie had been in a condition any whit better or gentler, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the King and the Clergie here were ſo ſtiffe againſt the Court of <hi>Rome;</hi> for what the King &amp; our great Primate did deny to the Pope, it was intended to be reſerved in the ſame rigor to themſelves. The Papiſt properly ſo called in <hi>Canterburies</hi> ſenſe ſo much to be abominated, was he which maintained a ſuprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the Pope here in <hi>England</hi> altogether incompatible with the oath of Allegeance, and not agreeing with the Archbiſhops Metropoliticall power. Without any Treaty, without any dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty at all, all Popery which was not Popery properly ſo called; that is, all Popety ſo far as the people and inferiour Clergie were intereſſed in it, ſo it did not ſavour of the Court of <hi>Rome;</hi> nay, let it ſavour of the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſo it did not derogate any thing from the King <hi>in temporalibus,</hi> or the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhops independecy <hi>in ſpiritualibus;</hi> ſo far it was acceptable to the Prelates, and they would be aſſiſting to recommend, or inforce it on all others. This was the ſumme of our recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation with <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 Secondly, I come now to the two parties which were to be reconciled; and they were the Proteſtants and Papiſts, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided hitherto by the Puritanes: our <hi>Venetian</hi> reſolves not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly who are, but alſo what are Proteſtants and Puritanes both; and as for the Papiſts, the third great faction, they need no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription at all: if we deſire to know who are Proteſtants, our
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:63000:9"/>
               <hi>Venetian</hi> tels us, <hi>They conſiſt of the King, the Nobles Titular, that is, the Court Lords, and Gentlemen, or ſuch of the Peerage and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, as are enobled and raiſed to more than ordinary favours, and honors, beſides almoſt all the Prelates, and both the Vniverſities: If we deſire to know what it is that denominates them Proteſtants, tis intimated in this that they hate Puritanes more than they hate Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, that they eaſily combine with Papiſts to extirpate Puritanes, that they are ſuch as have not ſo ingaged themſelves to the Reformed Religion, but that they have ſince ſet themſelves to reduce them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves againe to the old practiſe of their forefathers: that they are only very opinative in excluding the Popes ſupremacy, and by this meanes have occaſioned the Catholicks, which frequented Proteſtant Churches for</hi> 12 <hi>yeares after the Reformation to ſequeſter them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</hi> If we deſire to know who are Puritanes, <hi>He tels us, they conſist of ſome Biſhops, all the Gentry and Communalty, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are the moſt potent of all the three parties:</hi> If we deſire to know what Puritanes are, and what is intended in that deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination; he tels us, <hi>They are ſuch as received the diſcipline of the French and Netherlanders, &amp; hold not the Engliſh Reformation to bee ſo perfect, as that which Calvin inſtituted at Geneva: That they hate Catholick more than they hate Proteſtants, that they would be caſily quitted were it not for ſome great Patrons of theirs at Court, who for private ends take them into Protection.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If this be a true account given (as it ſeemes to me beyond all doubt) the greateſt part of the Gentry and Communalty of <hi>England,</hi> under the odious terme of Puritanes is to be op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, and deſtroyed meerely becauſe they honour <hi>Calvin,</hi> and are averſe from the Pope. The name of Proteſtant alſo is to be appropriated to the King, the Nobilitie, the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, and Vniverſities, meerely becauſe they hate the Gentry and Commonalty, or the Generality therof more then they hate Papiſts: and laſtly the Papiſt and the Proteſtant that they may be more fully incorporated, both of them ſhall be grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and their Vnion ſolemnized, as it were with the ruine of the third and moſt Potent party of the Kingdom.</p>
            <p>This was that great and godly worke which was ſo mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:63000:10"/>by Doctor Heylin and and other Court Chaplaines of late; this was that rare bloudy machination which his Grace of <hi>Canterbury</hi> and the other Grandees of our Church recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to us, as the pious inclination of the times, and as a more beautiful reſtoration of the Goſpel, then that w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> 
               <hi>Luther</hi> and <hi>Calvin</hi> labour'd to advance. <hi>Rome</hi> had not ſuch pregnant hopes of regaining <hi>England</hi> fifty yeares agoe: for then (as a great Romaniſt complained) oppoſition was made, not onely by a puritan-City, and a puritan-Parliament, but a puritan-Queene alſo. It ſhould ſeem the City of <hi>London</hi> was puritani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call from the beginning, and ſo was the Parliament; in which two is comprized all that is noble and worthy in the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>England:</hi> but who would imagine that ſo inconſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable a party as the Papiſts and ſemi-Papiſts were in Queene <hi>Elizabeths</hi> dayes, ſhould dare to aſperſe, not only the whole kingdome, but even the Queene her ſelfe? and who can wonder, if in theſe times, London and the Parliament have new brands of diſgrace, worſe then that of Puritane fixed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, (The King himſelfe now appearing againſt them) if they could not goe unbranded when that unparallell'd Lady profeſſed with them? yet we cannot aſcribe this ſo much to the policy of the Clergy, as the blockiſhneſſe of the Laity, that the Hierarchy prevailes ſo far: for if whole Cities, whole Parliaments, whole Nations, are to be conquered with the meere calumnious words of Puritane, Roundhead, Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt. &amp;c. Who is able to ſtand before them? can it be imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned that the ſame faction ſhould forbeare to call us Round<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heads which upbraided Q. <hi>Elizabeth</hi> as a Puritane, eſpecially, when by their comming upon the King they have gotten that advantage now? Which then they had no hopes to get, nor can it be imagined that that party will fall from its prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and hopes, rather then to ſatisfie ſo ſottiſh a generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it will take the paines to invent one reviling term of ſcur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rility? ſurely the world for theſe many ages has had better experience both of the malice and ſubtilty of Rome.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Thirdly, the meanes uſed for the effecting of this reconcili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:63000:10"/>and for the ſure tranſacting and cloſe carrying of it on, are now to be conſidered. The King it ſhould ſeeme thought that without all ſcanda<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l he might receive an Embaſſadour from the Pope, as well as from other Catholick Princes, and upon the propoſition of the ſame by <hi>Panzani</hi> himſelfe to the Queene, and to ſome others of power about the King by <hi>Panzani's</hi> friend; the thing ſeemed very reaſonable, ſo that the Nuntio to be ſent over were no Prieſt: howſoever for more privacies ſake, it was ordered, that the Nuntio ſhould addreſſe himſelf to the Queen, and not to the King immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately; and that the pretended buſineſſe of his addreſſe ſhould be to mediate a reconciliation betwixt the Regulars and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars in England. This would better blinde the jealous Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritanes, and make the true intent of the negotiation the more involved: and the caſe of Dr. <hi>Smith</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>Chalcedon</hi> expelled by the perſecution of the Ieſuites, for claiming ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction as Vniverſal ordinary in <hi>England,</hi> ſerved well at this time for a ſpecious colour. Reaſon of ſtate none could be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged for any intercourſe betweene England and Rome, therfore the Church affairs muſt be the ſubject of our Embaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, the Ieſuites and the Seculars were imbroyled in ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation, &amp; twas for the benefit of Rome to appeaſe the heat of it. Without all doubt the Romiſh Councell <hi>De propaganda ſide</hi> would not entertaine agents from us to ſettle union be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene Calviniſts and Lutherans, or betweene Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrants and Contra-Remonſtrants: but we that have no ſuch councell nor no ſuch deſigne, inſtead of nouriſhing enmity amongſt our adverſaries, allay it, and in ſtead of allaying enmity amongſt friends, nouriſh it. Nothing can more cleerely ſhew, that the Court of England ſtands not diſaffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to the proſperity of Rome, then this endevour of making atonement betwixt the oppoſite Champions of that religion, and yet this was but the ſhell of the deſigne, the kernell had more miſchiefe in it: for we may underſtand by our <hi>Venetian,</hi> that <hi>Panzani</hi> out of his great circumſpection and fineneſſe, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving matured the buſineſſe of generall reconciliation, ſo well
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:63000:11"/>for the further covering of his true deſigne, he did apply him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe after, to his pretended negotiation. And therefore upon the 22 of <hi>November</hi> 1635, almoſt a yeare after his arrivall here procured ſome accord betwixt the Seculars and Regulars, though the Ieſuites would not come in. The truth is, the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites were then the principall body of the Regulars, govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them (as they do ſtill alſo) the beſt families of <hi>England,</hi> nay the very Court it ſelfe, and ſo they not ſubmitting to the accord, 'twas but nugatory, and a meere umbrage to all the world, except the phlegmaticall dull Engliſh. Nay it is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently proved by our <hi>Venetian, that all pacification betwixt the Ieſuites &amp; Regulars is impoſsible, wherupon if Con comply with the Ieſuites, it is the ſame thing as if he did abandon the Seculars, and it is to be doubted that the buſineſſe of Religion will be rather hindered than promoted thereby.</hi> And what greaterinſtance need we of the Ieſuites predominance in <hi>Eng.</hi> than this, that notwithſtanding the diſtaſt of <hi>Canterb.</hi> and his deare, confident <hi>Chicheſter,</hi> they can excite the Popes ordinary here, nay, &amp; without all regard to the Colledge of <hi>Sorbona,</hi> &amp; to the Popes own intereſt, they dare inveigh not only againſt the perſon of ſome, but againſt the function of all Biſhops? Wherefore the accommodation betwixt Seculars and Regulars, being ſo uſeles to Proteſtants, &amp; ſo hopeles to Papiſts; we muſt not doubt but ſome deſigne of more conſequence was obſcured under that pretext, for when we heare that the Pope and Cardinall <hi>Barbarini</hi> diſpat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched ſo many perſons, of ſuch quality hither, &amp; that the King ſtood bare at their audience, and manifeſted ſo much grace in their reception, and that the Q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. and all the great Lords and Ladies, with extraordinary preſents, and frequent viſits, both given and taken, ſtudied to do ſuch honor to them, the matter in hand cannot ſeem ordinary. Tis true, the Arch-biſhop would not perſonally treat with <hi>Panzani; Windebank</hi> his crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture was to intervene therin, neither could <hi>Panzani</hi> treat with the Archbiſhop, but by <hi>Franſciſ a Sanct Clara</hi> his friend on the other ſide, but this was meerely for ſecrecies ſake; for we know well what factions ſoever were in our Court, <hi>Panzani was not
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:63000:11"/>unacceptable to any, by the meanes of Windebank he obtained grace with Canterburies party and by the meanes of Cottington he held correſpondency with that party which was adverſe. Panzani</hi> though not addicted to the Regulars, yet wanted no acceptance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the <hi>Cottingtonians,</hi> and <hi>Con</hi> though in grace with the Ieſuites, yet loſt no eſteem with the <hi>Canterburians.</hi> All ſides conſpire to undo Puritanes, as if our Saviour were again to be crucified; <hi>Herod</hi> in this buſines can lay aſide all emulations &amp; variance with <hi>Pilate,</hi> and <hi>Pilate</hi> can as peaceably ſhake hands with <hi>Herod.</hi> It may be juſtly ſurmiſed alſo, that when there was ſo amicable &amp; generall a concurrence betwixt <hi>Canterbury, Chicheſter</hi> and the other 8. Biſhops, (amongſt whom we may boldly nominate <hi>Gloceſter</hi>) as alſo <hi>Portland, Cotting. Windebank</hi> and ſo many other Lay Grandees cooperating in this zealous work of Reconciliation, the order of the Ieſuites was not in truth ſo odious to the <hi>Canterburians</hi> as was pretented openly at other times.</p>
            <p n="4">4 We are now to conſider the advantage, which was the maine motive or allurement to invite the King to this Recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation. That cup of fornication which the <hi>Circe</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> (as the Scripture deſcribes it) mingles and prepares for the Ks. of the earth, muſt needs be very delicious to the ſenſe, aſwell as it is pernitious to the underſtanding; it muſt needs pleaſe, as well as intoxicate, or elſe why ſhould the great Potentates of the world be more apt to yeeld to the infatuation of it than common perſons? That it does inebriate or deboſh the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, muſt be conſented to by all that conſent to the truth of Scripture, and that there is a purpoſe of miſchiefe in that ſtrumpet, whoſe intoxications are ſo ſtrong to captivate, and delude, cannot be doubted; the maine knot &amp; difficulty is, what the ingredients are, which render the Compoſition ſo ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhing and ſweet to the palate of Princes. Our <hi>Venetian</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives, <hi>That the allurement or advantage is ſomething temporal, and not religious, for in his cenſure great Princes &amp; Polititians in their ſoules make no account of Religion, though in ſhew they always indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to appeare extreamely zealous, and ſeverely inflict exemplary
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:63000:12"/>puniſhments upon all ſuch as temerate the purity of it; ſome men, he admits, may embrace Religion in ſincerity, as it leades to true happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, but tis hard for him to imagine that mighty Monarchs, &amp; their neareſt privados ſhould honor it at all, but for its ſecular commodities as it inclines the people to ſubjection, and preſerves States from com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion.</hi> Neither muſt we cenſure this cenſure, as utterly cauſles and injurious, for Paganiſm, Mahome aniſm, Iudaiſm, Papiſm, Socinianiſme, divide all the world amongſt them, except one final inconſiderable remainder, &amp; divide that remainder into 10 parts, and ſcarce one of thoſe 10 is indued with that true power and tincture of Religion, which Scripture names rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration; and if we yet make another ſubdiviſion, the mighty, the politick, the honorable of this world will ſcarce make up the 10 of that tenth part. The maine bulk of mankind, either makes no profeſſion at all to regard Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or elſe profeſſeth a regard meerely for the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>porall conveniences which attend religion, or elſe falſly &amp; hypocritically, reſt in the meere ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow or ex ernal formalities of it. Our K. has been always bred up in the Prot<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> relig<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and with deep vows has expreſt often his ſincere adherence to it, though our <hi>Venetian</hi> therefore being a Papiſt cenſured according to the principles of a Papiſt; for my part I ſhall nevertheles have none but charitable thoughts of our Kings hearty eſteeme of Religion in general, and of the Proteſtant religion in particular. Tis not credible to me, that all religions ſhould be indifferent, or of the like efficacy in the eſteem of our King, or that the Romiſh religion ſhould ſeem ſpiritually more efficacious to him, than Proteſtantiſme, ſome advantages (I conceive) of a ſecular, political nature might have the force to diſpoſe his heart to a reconciliation with <hi>Rome,</hi> but I am moſt confident, that no ſpiritual advantage was aimed at therein. For if the advantage had been celeſtiall, and ſuch as did appertaine immediatly to the ſoule, then all times had bin alike opportune for reconciliation with the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> nay the firſt opportunity was moſt to be embraced; but in this ſpeech or the Kings cited by our <hi>Venetian,</hi> a fitnes of ſeaſon ſeems to be impli'd for the inviting to a preſent reconciliatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:63000:12"/>There is no doubt then remaining, nor nothing fit for our inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry but what temporall advantage it was, which the K. expected and promiſt to himſelf, &amp; what kind of reconciliation it was w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> he thought fit to conclude with <hi>Rome.</hi> As for the reconciliation that has been already ſpoken to, and as it is uncertaine what the K. intended in his own breaſt, &amp; how far he reſolved to comply with the Pope; ſo it is moſt certain, that the Biſh. &amp; thoſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellors of his, which were moſt intimate with him, and moſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive in the negotiation with <hi>Panzani,</hi> &amp;c. intended a totall alre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of religion, &amp; that he was groſſely abuſed &amp; deceived by them, if he himſelf intended otherwiſe. This has bin made ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently manifeſt; I am now to make it as manifeſt, if I can, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in thoſe temporal advantages alſo, wherby the King was ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licited, and incited to deſcend to any agreement at all with the Pope in any degree whatſoever, he was as groſſely abuſed &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived alſo. The ſacerdotall Empire of <hi>Rome,</hi> though it be foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded upon nothing elſe but meere deluſions &amp; incantations (as the holy S. of God himſelfe perpetually inculcates to us) yet to fleſh &amp; bloud thoſe deluſions &amp; incantatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s are ſo powe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ful, that we may truely ſay it is a Throne very cunningly erected, and as firmely under-propped. The Romiſh Potion at firſt had only ſpiritual ingredients in it, the Biſhops were compelled to act ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctity even almoſt to the life, before Princes would ſubject them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, &amp; at that time nothing but heauen was the allurement to d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſpoſe Mon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rhs to ſuch ſubjectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Nevertheles though we may wonder that innocent, wel affected Ks. &amp; Emperors ſhould be ſo blinded with abu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dance of zeale, as to think that they could not ſufficiently glorify God with their royalty, unles they diſrobed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelves of ſome part of it, to communicate the ſame to Prieſts, who muſt needs grow the more te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poral, &amp; not the more ſpiritual therby; yet that error was more excuſable then ours is in theſe lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter times. Prin. now adays (except ſome very few that are excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding weak in their intellectuals) do not ſuffer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelves to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentated &amp; made drunk with any conceits of the Popes holines, if the Pope did not further ſweeten his cup with promiſes of grandour &amp; ſafety, and other temporal additions, 'twould ſcarce relliſh in theſe depraved, yet quick-ſighted times.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:63000:13"/>
            <p>Can any man imagine that <hi>Hen.</hi> 4, in <hi>France</hi> did totally, or King <hi>Iames</hi> in <hi>Eng.</hi> partially comply with <hi>Rome</hi> for conſcience ſake? no, tis impoſſible that ſuch fine ſpirits &amp; firme intellects, ſhould be ſo far transformed by any Circean compound drink whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever; doubtleſſe that which drew them in, to carouſe was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing proper, and peculiarly qualified for their relliſhes, and in probability it was reſpect of ſafety and ſecurity, rather than ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of power and ſupremacy. That power which Princs firſt parted with to the Pope, for religious reaſons, inabled him to frame a great party of Clergy-men, and Regular Orders, and to himſelf al that were eminent for learning, policy, &amp; reputed pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; &amp; being thus inabled, ſuch Princes as were not to be beguild by his pretences, he after oppreſſed by treachery. Wherefore now ſome Princes ſtoop to him for feare of damage, <hi>ut non no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceat;</hi> others for hope of benefit <hi>ut proſit,</hi> and though his Empire be now in a great declination, and the world begins both to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie themſelves againſt his powder, poyſon &amp; poynards on the one ſide; and to diſcover the falſity of his promiſes on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide; yet ſtill his induſtry never failes him. Howſoever thoſe Princes which ſubmit to the Pope for feare, are more worthy of blame, than thoſe which ſubmit for gaine; for ſcarce ever did God leave any juſt Prince to the cruelty of the Popes Emiſſaries, nor ſcarce ever was it known, that they came to time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ends, which ſuccumbed to the Pope out of feare, as <hi>Hen.</hi> the 4 did, and as King <hi>Iames</hi> may be ſuſpected to have done. But tis advantage that is the Popes maine bayte, eſpecially where Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces value Religion <hi>for the generall profit which redounds from it, to humane ſociety, than for any other excellence diſcerned in it;</hi> as our <hi>Venetian</hi> obſerves. And yet the miſery and miſchief reſts not here, for as our great Pote<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tates are not religious enough to addict themſelves to divine worſhip, without reſpect of ſecular ends, ſo neither are they wiſe enough to pierce into the reality &amp; truth of thoſe ends. To ſerve the Pope does not ſo really adva<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative of Princes, as to remain under Gods allegiance, yet the Pope gaines that obedience by empty promiſes, which God cannot receive by full aſſurances.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:63000:13"/>
            <p>Amongſt other Princes; it ſeems (at leaſt propable out of this diſcourſe of our <hi>Venetian</hi>) King <hi>Charles</hi> hath inclined his ear in ſome part, to the deluſory bewitching allurements of <hi>Rome</hi> in this point of temporall advantage, for though Popery un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the groſſe notion of Popery, (I believe) was never appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of by our King, yet under the maſque of qualifying, and dulcifying diſtinctions, it is to be feared it found ſome accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, as being a profeſſion more diſpoſing Subjects to ſecu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and blind obedience, then Proſteſtantiſme.</p>
            <p>This is the Popes ſole fortreſſe, upon this impregnable rock shis throne planted, it is not ſo much his pretended predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſour <hi>Peters</hi> confeſſion, as this deluſion that he builds upon, ſo that now the gates of Hell are not formidable to him. So long as Princes covet to be abſolute, and ſo long as Popery is belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to favour abſolute dominion, ſo long the See of <hi>Rome</hi> thinks it ſelf ſecure, againſt all mines and barteries whatſoever. Nevertheleſſe it is the dull ſollie of Princes to expect tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall advantages from <hi>Rome,</hi> or to ſuppoſe the Reformed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion is more adverſe to Monarchy, then the Popiſh. Our <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netian</hi> tells us <hi>that the intentions both of the Court of Rome, and the Court of England, are contrary, and that in Secular things eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially, for (ſaith he) it is not ſo much for the extirpation of other hereſies, as for the eſtabliſhing his own Supremacy, that the Pope ſtrives in purſuance of his old pretences, and whereas on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, the Court of England aimes not at any alteration in faith, ſo much as the toleration of the oath of Supremacie, this the Pope knowes to be contrary to his Maximes, and inconſiſtent with his temporall grandour, and therefore no accord</hi> can be poſſible be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt them upon theſe terms: wherefore our great negotiators which were to treat with <hi>Panzani, Con,</hi> and <hi>Roſetti,</hi> what did they elſe, but abuſe the King, propoſing to him ſuch tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall advantages, as they well knew were uncompaſſable? and contracting with another partie who might gain much, but was certaine to loſe nothing. But ſome will ſay, are not the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of <hi>Spaine, France, Germany,</hi> &amp;c. more unlimited in their
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:63000:14"/>power over their ſubjects then the Princes of <hi>England, Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marke, Holland, &amp;c.</hi> And is not this a good demonſtration that the Catholick religion favours royalty more then the Proteſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants? I anſwer no; for this proves that ſubjects are more miſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, but not that Princes are more abſolute amongſt the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, for as much as where the Pope prevailes, there is a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dominion and rivalty in rule, and this Proteſtant Princes are freed from.</p>
            <p>Neither is this Co-dominion ſo light a thing as ſome men think, for the Popes yoke is a hard yoke, and the Popes bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then is a heavy burthen, he is Antichriſt in this, as in all other things, that is, contrary to Chriſt.</p>
            <p>A late Venetian Embaſſador being in diſcourſe here at his owne table, about entertaining of the Popes Nuntios, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtulated openly in this manner; <hi>What wonder is this that the King being freed from Rome, ſhould be ſo inclineable to ſubject his neck to the yoake againe? Could we at Venice once fully acquit our ſelves of this bondage, we ſhould be ſufficiently carefull and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to keep our ſelves for ever free.</hi> And this ſpeech was the more remarkable, in regard that the <hi>Venetians</hi> better know what the Popes claimes are <hi>in ſpiritualibus,</hi> &amp; <hi>in ordine ad ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritualia,</hi> then our Engliſh doe; and yet though of all Catholicks they are the wiſeſt, and have beſt rampired themſelves againſt the exceſſe of the Popes juriſdiction; yet we ſee there is ſtill ſome thing remaining in the ſpirituall yoke, that grievs their necks and drawes ſome regret from them, the ſecret of all is but this, (for to the Great Lords of the earth, it remaines ſtill a ſecret and unfathomable, though to true Proteſtents it be a plaine ordinary naked truth) Popery as it doth more counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance and uphold cruell tyranny in Princes, ſo it doth alſo more foment diſſention, and rebellion in ſubjects then the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Religion.</p>
            <p>And there is no contradiction at all in this (none but halfe witted men will think ſo) for whilſt Princes will allow the Pope more then is his due, he will aſſiſt in any oppreſſion whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:63000:14"/>but let any thing be denied to him, and then he preſent-looſeneth the bonds of allegiance, making Subjects as unjuſt ſcourges to their Lords, as he had made the Lords before to their Subjects, what countreyes doe not abound with ſtories of this kind? it would be meere loſſe of time to ſet forth what ſeas of bloud have been ſhed in <hi>Europe,</hi> by unnaturall civil broils, raiſed betwixt Subjects and their Lords in the Popes quarrells meerely, I ſhall deſire all true Engliſh men to read Mr. <hi>Prinne<hi rend="sup">c</hi>s</hi> late treatiſes, concerning this ſubject, and to compare them with hiſtories of other countries. The Popes promiſes to Kings, are like the tempters to our Saviour, all theſe royalties and glories will I beſtow upon you, but with this proviſo, that you then proſtrate your ſelves to ſerve me, but what is that ſervice which he requires? that they may endure a baſer vaſſallage under him then their Subjects do under them.</p>
            <p>On the contrary the Proteſtant Religion ſeaſons us, with ſuch unſtained loyalty, that Princes do preſume thereupon, &amp; fear the leſſe to grieve, &amp; provoke us, as by <hi>Contzens</hi> the Jeſuits ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſements, &amp; the practice of divers Princes in <hi>Europe</hi> of late is teſtified too clearly, well may we wonder then at the front<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe impudence of ſuch Papiſts as upbraide Proteſtants with diſobedience to Magiſtracy, eſpecially when they charge it as a ſin reſulting, &amp; iſſuing out of the Proteſtant principles, them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. What doth <hi>Barclay</hi> imagine of his readers ſtupidity, when in his book <hi>contra Monarchomachos,</hi> he inveighes againſt his countrey man <hi>Buchanan,</hi> as injurious to Royalty, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes this, as an effect, or product of the Proteſtant Religion?</p>
            <p>His Relgion was ever infamous for excommunicating, murthering, depoſing Princes, and imbruing nations in unnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, treaſonable, execrable warres, whereas the Proteſtant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion equally abhorres both cruelty in princes, and diſloyalty in Subiects, aiming at nothing but that Kingly prerogative and popular liberty, may be even ballanced; and yet this foule rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, here inverts nature, calling white black, and black white.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:63000:15"/>
            <p>The King of <hi>England</hi> hath ſome Subiects wherein none hath an intereſt, but himſelf, and he hath other Subiects wherein the Pope hath an intereſt as well as himſelf, the firſt are Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, the ſecond are Iriſh, in whether Nations loyalty he may rather confide I cannot tell, (for at this preſent he bends him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with more violence againſt the Englſh, then Iriſh) but the end will reveal to the confuſion of his malignant ſeducers, that there was nothing but fidelity in Engliſh Proteſtants, nor nothing but perfidie in Iriſh Papiſts, I ſhall uſe no other inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: If there be any curſe impendent over the Nation, both King and People, it is this, that this truth is not yet ſufficiently credited and acknowledged.</p>
            <p>But to our preſent negotiation again, it ſeemed to our <hi>Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian, that the King aimed at ſuch a diſpenſation from the Pope, as that his Catholick Subiests might reſort to our Proteſtant Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, and take the oath of Supremacy, and fidelity, and that the Popes iuriſdiction here ſhould be declared, to be but of humane right,</hi> &amp;c. but what needed the King to ſeek theſe things from the Pope? or what hope was there to obtaine them at all? and if they were to be obtained, but not without the loſſe of other things, ten times more precious, and profitable to the King, what advantage was in them?</p>
            <p>We cannot apprehend that the King ſhould expect any good from <hi>Rome</hi> of himſelf, ſome ſtrong inchanting ſolicitation there muſt be, to induce him, and that by ſuch, as aimed not at his, but their own intereſts, and this our <hi>Venetian</hi> layes open and makes clear enough for he tells us <hi>that the Court of</hi> Rome <hi>treated according to its own maxime, and in purſuance of its old pretences.</hi> The Popes end was temporall grandour, and what co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ld all the Popes vaſſalls, here more expect then his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement? but the Pope and his party, were but Treaters of one ſide, the queſtion is, who were Treaters on the other ſide, and what it was, which they were to treate for. This queſtion is without queſtion, for the Merchants of our ſide, were our Pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ates, <hi>ſome whereof being ſingle, were to be made Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalls,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:63000:15"/>and others were to receive penſions from Rome,</hi> as our <hi>Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian</hi> tells us. The Proteſtant Religion doth not ſo much affect the outward opulence, pomp, and ſplendour, of the Church, (that is of Clergy men) as the Popiſh doth, and therefore the main body of the Clergy, and the Univerſities have been long conſpiring to alter Religion, at leaſt in that point, and rather then faile in that, they care not how they deboſh the Church inducing an hotohpodge (as Mr. <hi>Cheynell</hi> has well obſerved of Arminianiſme, Popery, Socinianiſne, any thing rather then a plaine Goſpell. If <hi>Canterbury</hi> may not be allowed to be <hi>Alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius Orbis Papa,</hi> as ſome of his predeceſſors were called, and as able to give check to the Crowne of <hi>England,</hi> and if Schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ars generally may not inſult and lord it in Church and ſtate, as the uſe was amongſt our ignorant forefathers, they will make a league with <hi>Rome,</hi> nay with hell it ſelf, rather then endure it. <hi>The Religion of Scotland is a naſty invention, the diſcipline of Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neva is a profaine confuſion, the City of London is a neſt of Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts, the Parliament a croud of croundheads: All Proteſtants that are not for beautified Altars, gilt Organs, clinquant copes, are worſe Chriſtians then the Romiſh Catholicks:</hi> how ſoever the true Proteſtant deſires not to ſee the Clergy deſpicable, or the houſe of God to be without bread, or order confounded in the Church, theſe are ſcandals invented to make all men odious that are not addicted to the Popiſh gaity &amp; tyranny of Prieſts. That Reformation which the Parliament aimes at will avoide all unjuſtice and extreames, and if the Clergy ſtand not in their own light, Religion will flouriſh and the Church proſper bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then they have done hitherto: for the Vine which is the moſt naturall reſemblance of the Church that can be, proves equally unfertile by luxuriance, when her branches for want of pruning ſpread abroad too wildly, as it does by indurance when ſhee bleeds two prodigally under the dreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers knife, And this cannot be unknowne to the Parliament.</p>
            <p n="5">5 We come now to vew the true obſtickles and impe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of this Reconciliation, one hindrance was Sr. Toby
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:63000:16"/>
               <hi>Mathewes</hi> his ambition, who thinking his imployment leſſned, and his perſon cheapened by the comming over of feig. <hi>Pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zani,</hi> and not finding ſuch compliance from <hi>Panzani,</hi> as he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, openly expreſſed himſelfe an adverſary to his under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takings. the great ſtomack alſo of the Jeſuites, who before had the ſway at Court; did not well brook a lay Legate here in England, and if the reconciliation thrived, they did perhaps feare that the Engliſh Nation might rather incline to favour the ſeculars then themſelves. Then the Pope doubtleſſe (with reverence be it ſpoken to his infallibility) was a little too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſticall at firſt in his moving towards us, he ſaw us ſo precipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate in our pace towards him that he thought he himſelf might ſafely ſtand upon rigorous punctilio's. The King required from the Pope onely ſuch naturall allegiance of his ſubjects as other Catholicke Princes uſe to have paid them, without futher diſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inguiſhing, and yet his holineſſe did conceive it was too much to tolarate this oath for the aſſurance of that. His holineſſe thought it rather fit that the very words formerly conceived and enacted by the ſtates of the whole kingdome, ſhould be preſently expunged or altered: and though the King was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented to qualifie and correct the letter of the law, by a mild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er declaration, and interpretation, yet even that was not held ſatisfaction enough.</p>
            <p>In the next place alſo our Prelates were contented to allow the Pope a priority above all Biſhops, but a ſuperiority ſeemed more then due, eſpecially in <hi>England</hi> the Arch <hi>Biſhop</hi> was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to be the ſupream Ordinary himſelf, and yet his holines did not thinke it agreeable to his Vice-Godſhip to admit of that honour as due to the Arch-Biſhop. The diſpute was not whether the Arch-Biſhop ſhould execute that office in his own name and right, or by allowance and deputation from the Pope, nor was there any clauſe of <hi>ſalvo jure</hi> to either of them, as yet thought on. theſe were tender points not to be inſiſted on too roughly, at ſuch a time as this, when bothſides were ſo far re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved of a reconciliation before hand. There muſt be a more
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:63000:16"/>mind and eaſie way of compoſing things then ſo: for as the Pope had rather we ſhould remaine Proteſtants, and ſo deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate of ſalvation, then that his ſupremacy ſhould be too farre im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peached; ſo <hi>Canterbury</hi> had rather we ſhould not turne Papiſts then that his Primacie ſhould be too farre diſabled. The bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain therefore at firſt unqualified was thus. The Pope demand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to have a Legate in <hi>England</hi> that ſhould be a Biſhop, and not favour the oath of Allegiance, on the other ſide the King here would have the oath of allegiance favoured, and the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops thought it needleſſe, for the Pope to have any other a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents, or deputies here beſides themſelves. This difference could hardly be compoſed all the time of Seig. <hi>Panzani,</hi> but at laſt the Biſhops durſt not wholly neglect the Kings intereſt, and ſo the oath of allegiance was included in the bargain, and the King would not oppoſe the Biſhops intereſt, and ſo a lay Legate was agreed upon, and it was for the Popes honour that a Legate ſhould be for the ſaving of his authority, and therefore becauſe the Pope could not withſtand both King, and Biſhops, ſuch a Legate was agreed upon as ſhould favour the oath, yet be no Biſhop. It was preſſed home to the Pope, that the Archbiſhop and his party, were paſſionate ſeekers of this Reconciliation. and in order, and preparation thereunto, had already brought in many Rites, Ceremonies, and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, nearly approching the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and that if the work were not ſpeeded during his life time, greater difficulties and re-incounters were likely to interpoſe after his death, and yet for a good ſpace the Pope thought the conditions too unequall. So little weight and proportion did the ſoules of mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions hold, in compariſon of one temporall flower, of the popes garland, and therefore <hi>Panzanies</hi> skill, and induſtry, for a whole yeare could ſcarce maſter theſe animoſities, and facili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate the buſineſſe for his next ſucceſſours: nevertheleſſe, the Pope at laſt, grew more a Courtier, and ſtooped a little to a ſmoothy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pliance by his more crafty miniſters, <hi>Con,</hi> &amp; <hi>Roſetti</hi> and now the plot of the agreement is perfected, and there wants nothing, but the putting of it into execution. Without a
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:63000:17"/>effected but by their utter ſubverſion, the wiſhed reconciliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on could not yet be conſummated, and the Puritanes being the greater part of the Kingdome by farre, this taske muſt needs be very cumberſome, <hi>Confeſsion</hi> (as our <hi>Venetian</hi> heard ſay) <hi>was a thing held fit to be urged upon us by violence, but fear of commoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hindered it,</hi> and we may very probably conjecture that ſome other groſſer points of Popery had been obtruded upon us alſo by the higher powers, but that the curſed indiſpoſition of the Puritanes was ſuch, that there was great hazzard in the attempt Howſoever our ſtout Prelates were not out of all hope of carrying their deſigne, either by fraud or force, or a mixture of both, and therefore ſeeing things ſo equally poized in <hi>England Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> they were reſolved that no meere haz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard ſhould wholly deter them from adventuring the utmoſt. <hi>Scotland</hi> appeared wholly almoſt puritanicall, but to counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poiſe that, <hi>Ireland</hi> appeared as generally Popiſh, and for <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> though the major part there was puritanicall, yet the more potent in place and authority<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and the more exquiſite in ſubtilti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, or rather treachery was Popiſh or Proteſtant, that is inclined to combine with Papiſts, and therfore in all this there was little odds, to diſanimate them, neither was their any feare of forraign forces: for under the deceitfull pretence of our head-ſhip and aſſociation, the Proteſtants in <hi>Germany</hi> and <hi>France</hi> were allready much weakned and betrayed, and made jealous of adhering to us, they being brought to ſuch a condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that they could not helpe themſelves at home, much leſſe annoy enemies abroad. Alſo the King of <hi>Denmarke</hi> and Prince of <hi>Aurange,</hi> though Proteſtants, yet were Polititians, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the intereſt of Royalty, would queſtionles prevaile more with them, then the intereſt of Religion. It would pleaſe them better to ſee the <hi>Prerogative</hi> gained in <hi>England,</hi> to the damage of Religion, then religion to proſper, by the diminution of Prerogative. It onely remains then that in <hi>England</hi> they plot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Reconciliation be firſt put in execution, and advanced by as ſlow inſenſible degrees, as may be, and great art muſt be u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, when Churches, Altars, &amp;c. beg in to be decored;
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:63000:17"/>be made to believe, not that popery is to be induced, but that a faire reconciliation between both Churches is to be procured; and not that <hi>Proteſtantiſme</hi> is to be at all in any conſiderable matter changed, but that <hi>Puritaniſme</hi> be exterminated. Alſo when not onely faire allurements, but the two great <hi>Carnificines</hi> of the Land, The <hi>Star-Chamber</hi> and <hi>High-Commiſsion</hi> have by rigor prevailed as far as may be; and when by all other meanes the <hi>Engliſh</hi> are inured, and familiarized to ſome popiſh rites under the faire pretence of conforming to Reverend Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Then the <hi>Scots</hi> (who are not ſo apt to be inamoured with the ſplendor and pomp of Church-men as we are) muſt be by all meanes aſſailed, and urged to union and conformity with the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And becauſe it is expected that the <hi>Scots</hi> ſhould be more jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of the leaſt incroachments of Poperie, and more adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turous to ſecure themſelves in ſuch jealouſie, and more unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous in their adventure; therefore their countrey is to be made the firſt Scene of the war. And ſince it would be too groſſe to impeach the whole Nation of <hi>Puritaniſme,</hi> therefore their crime muſt be rebellion; and the better to imbarque the <hi>Engliſh</hi> in the quarrell, that in the <hi>Scots</hi> they might deſtroy themſelves, ſome new diſguiſe muſt be put upon the war; it muſt be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulged, that in ſtead of ſettling Biſhops in their Sees, and bringing in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Lyturgie, the King has need to be eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed in his Throne, and <hi>Scotland</hi> to be preſerved from <hi>Anar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie.</hi> All the diſpute is; Whether Subjects may make re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance by force of Arms againſt a juſt, pious, clement Prince, the name of <hi>Bellum Epiſcopale</hi> is diſ-owned: the Title of the Lords annoynted will better ſupport the envie of theſe broyles; and it is ſuggeſted to the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> that both the Lawes and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives of <hi>Scotland</hi> are more <hi>Antimonarchicall</hi> then thoſe of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All theſe traines, notwithſtanding the <hi>Puritane</hi> faction in <hi>England</hi> (that is, all cordiall <hi>Proteſtants</hi>) abominated the grounds of that war, and in concluſion, the popiſh faction, and the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:63000:18"/>Nobility, Univerſities and Clergie, which onely chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge the name of <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> were not able to put the King in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſuch a condition of ſtrength, but that he was driven to give the <hi>Scots</hi> their demanded ſatisfaction. Hereupon likewiſe a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution is taken to ſummon a Parliament in <hi>England,</hi> as is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended for the disbanding of the two Armies, and compoſing theſe Nationall breaches; but ſome thinke, for the turning one or both theſe Armies another way, and raiſing farther diviſions in the bowels of <hi>England;</hi> but God ſo over-ruled the matter, that the <hi>Scots</hi> did peaceably retire, and our ſouldiers disband without attempting any thing againſt the Parliament.</p>
            <p>And now to recover life againe in this ſo foil'd an enterpriſe, nothing will ſerve, but that the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> (who were placed as in Ambuſcado for the purpoſe) muſt riſe all in Armes, and moſt perfidiouſly execute a ſecret bloody maſſacre upon all the <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh</hi> Proteſtants in that Kingdome. Doubtleſſe (if ever <hi>Rome</hi> ſhewed her excellent skill) 'twas in that ſilent deepe conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, if ever ſhe ſhewed her fiery zeale, 'twas in that horrid in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fernall Tragedie: If ever ſhe diſcovered her ſelfe to the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian world in her lively colours of whore, witch, murthereſſe, 'twas in this unparallel'd villany. By this meanes the Popiſh affaires are in better ſtate than ever; for <hi>Scotland</hi> ſtands gazing on, as if ſhe were loſt, in admiration, and <hi>Ireland</hi> is become not onely intire for the buſineſſe for its owne ſtrength, but is back'd alſo with ſome ſupply out of <hi>Flaunders,</hi> and other Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treyes; and even the Kings party in <hi>England</hi> (though they hold not open intelligence with them) yet act all the parts of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect friends and allyes to them.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Iriſh</hi> Rebells are ſecured by the diverſion of our Cava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liers here, and our Cavaliers here are ſecured by the diverſion made there by the Rebels; both ſides profeſſe and avow the ſame cauſe, and draw their ſwords againſt the ſame Parliament Round-heads; and were it not that our ſhipping did prevent their meetings, doubtleſſe our Cavaliers would procure ſome forces from <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the <hi>Iriſh</hi> would be ſupplyed with other
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:63000:18"/>neceſſaries out of <hi>England;</hi> and yet 'tis advantage to the popiſh abettors here, to diſclaime the advantage of Communion with their popiſh abettors there.</p>
            <p>That very Army alſo (which to the great exhauſting of the good party in <hi>England</hi> levied to oppugne the Rebels) is ſolli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited to joyne againſt thoſe, by whom it is levied; and ſupplies ſent for <hi>Ireland</hi> by the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> are intercepted by the Kings forces, and thus the Parliament (more unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate than the <hi>Pelican</hi>) makes wounds in her owne breaſt, to draw out blood, not for her friends, but for her enemies advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage. In this ſtrange confluence of unexpected miſchiefs, whilſt the Parliament finds her ſelfe ſo relinquiſh'd by her friends, ſo ſurrounded with enemies of contrary factions and pretences, and ſo undermined with daily new treaſons, Shee makes her moſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> humble addreſſe to the King to ſettle the <hi>Poſſe</hi> or <hi>Militia</hi> of this Kingdome, in faithfull well reputed hands; the King at firſt, in great darkneſſe, neither grants, nor ſeemes to deny the requeſt, he profeſſeth no diſlike to the perſons nominated, but alledgeth, that by this meanes, the Commiſſioners ſhould nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be authoriſed ſolely by his Commiſſion, nor ſhould be diſcharged at his meere pleaſure. The <hi>Scots</hi> had obtained this due righteous ſatisfaction before, and doubtleſſe had taken it as an utter defiance, or invaſion, had they not obtained it; but <hi>England</hi> is denyed ſo much right (even after its example, and the good conſequence thereof in <hi>Scotland</hi>) yet remaines too inſenſible of their owne danger in this fatall ſad denyall. Nevertheleſſe, the contrary faction takes this as the certaine trump of war; and leaving us to our deepe melancholly, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtirs it ſelfe towin the City of <hi>London,</hi> and all military perſons to the King; and though the City will not prove unfirme to the Parliament, yet the Cavaliers all flocke to the Court (and there careſſed by the Queene) vow themſelves to any deſigne whatſoever.</p>
            <p>Something alſo is plotted both againſt the Citie and Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but proving uneffectuall, becauſe both are ſo ſafe againſt
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:63000:19"/>the Popiſh partie and the Cavaliers: therefore it is preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that they are unſafe to the King and his Children, and it is ſpred abroad, that the King is in danger of being ſurprized by thoſe, who ſhould have been ſurprized by his, if God had not otherwiſe provided.</p>
            <p>The King is counſelled in the next place therefore to retire to ſome remote Port Towne of ſtrength, commodious for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit of Forces both forraine and domeſticall; and his eye is upon Hull, where a great Magazine of Armes is, but in that he is fore-ſtalled by the Parliament. This gives the King oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to levie men at York, for the ſafegard of his perſon, whilſt all intentions of an Army were ſolemnly abjured by himſelfe; and the ſame ſeconded by the Lords ſubſcriptions: and this was a good help to encreaſe his Gard into the propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of an Army, and to give good hope that hee might not only remaine ſafe in York, but alſo march forth to ſtorme Hull. But ſoft, I am not to paſſe the ſtorie of that march, that was the Rubicon of this war, and it is beyond my purpoſe to trace the buſineſſe any further; what hath ſince followed on both ſides, was enforced by theſe beginnings.</p>
            <p>I muſt now leave off my diſcoverie, <hi>Venit Heſpe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us;</hi> the day it ſelfe would faile mee, if I ſhould proſecute theſe things too far. He which takes all theſe premiſes into juſt conſideration, can want nothing elſe to convince and ſatisfie, who were the chiefe Incendiaries of this war, and who were the perſons that did commence and continue all our broyles. That the people of theſe our Kingdomes have of late yeares, ſince Queene <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeths</hi> death, ſo prodigiouſly degenerated, as of honourable to become generally diſhonourable, of loyall to become univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally diſloyall, of naturall to become totally unnaturall, is monſtrous to beleeve. But that King <hi>Iames</hi> and King <hi>Charles</hi> have varied from the government of Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and to hold a good underſtanding with Rome, have not been ſo fixedly devoted to the true intereſts of the reformed Religion, and their ſubjects proſperitie, as that bleſſed Lady was, is a truth that
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:63000:19"/>Heaven and earth will give teſtimony to. That ambitious Prelates have been our prime Fire-brands is manifeſt alſo; for without their ſtrong inchantments, our Kings would not have been ſo far alienated from us, and without that alienation, the Papiſts could not have ſo far trampled upon us. To compaſſe to themſelves an Empire above Princes, 'tas beene ever the charme of Prieſts to make promiſes and aſſurances, that they will elevate Princes as far above their Subjects, by an additi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of royaltie, and enlargement of prerogative. In this, all Prieſts conſpire, that prefer earth before Heaven, be they Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant or Popiſh, be they Engliſh or Romiſh, the difference is only this: the Engliſh Prelate affects Poperie for Tyrannies ſake, whereas the Romiſh prelate affects Tyranny for poperies ſake; but both affect both for their owne preferments ſake: for without Tyranny poperie cannot be enforced, and without poperie Tyranny cannot be ſupported; and as both cannot be eſtabliſht, but by a conſpiracie of both parties, ſo neither is that conſpiracie ſufficient, unleſſe the King alſo be won by it. Therefore in the Scots war it was ſuggeſted to the King, that the Crowne could not ſtand without the Myter, and therupon amongſt the Plebeians it was diſperſed and maintained, that the Biſhops fought to maintaine the Kings Crowne, not that the King fought to uphold the Biſhops Myter. And what diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence is there now in our caſe? Is not this war in England a meere reviving of that war which was in Scotland? Did not our prelats as openly imbark the King in their quarrell then, as they do now? And do not our prelats ſtruggle and ſtir as una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimouſly now, and ſtand for the ſame ends, and adhere to the ſame confederates, the papiſts, as they did then? One drop of water is not more like another, than the Scottiſh war is like this. And if it be objected, that the prelates now incenſe not the King againſt the Scots, and therefore there is ſomething new in the difference, more than was in that: and further, that they diſclaime and abhor the Iriſh rebellion, and therfore they combine not with papiſts. This anſwer is readily given. The
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:63000:20"/>Scots, 'tis true, are fairely entertained in words, but in deeds, all the hoſtilitie offered to us is aimed at them, and will reach them in the next place, their ruine is moſt inevitably invol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in ours, and the <hi>Stoccado</hi> that pierces it, will eaſily find a paſſage thorow our bodyes into theirs. I am ſure they are too wiſe a Nation to apprehend otherwiſe: ſo alſo for the <hi>Iriſh</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels 'tis as true, they are ignominiouſly entertained in words, but indeed all the hoſtility offered to us, is amity to them, 'tis armes, monies, ſupplies ſent to them; their protection is involved in our deſtruction, and our graves are their ſtrongeſt bulwarks. But oh! how is it, that I am conſtrained to menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that deteſtable word <hi>Ireland?</hi> How is it, that that habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Zim</hi> and <hi>Ohim</hi> ſhould enter my mind, to make there as diſmall a manſion of horror as it ſelfe? Had I ſuch fountains of teares in my head as <hi>Ieremiah</hi> had, to power out upon the ſlaine <hi>Proteſtants</hi> there, 'twould be ſome relaxation of griefe to me; or had I the bitterneſſe of ſoule which <hi>David</hi> had, when the Image of <hi>Iudas,</hi> traytorouſly imbrued in his Lord and Saviours blood repreſented it ſelfe to him, that I might power out all his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheticall execrations upo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them, and their poſterities, who have animated and enabled the rebels there; (eſpeciall, if any of them were <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> or of the <hi>Britiſh</hi> race, or in high place of authority) that, perhaps, would disburthen the too too preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing agonies of my ſpirit. But alas, alas, perhaps it is more ſeaſonable for me, to pray that the Celeſtiall groanes of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſes,</hi> than the infernall tortures of <hi>Iudas</hi> may be given by God to thoſe deeplingaged ſinners, upon whom this woful guilt lies. I now wander, and am loſt; I muſt returne to the buſineſſe in hand: I heare ſome ſay, that the Parliament did firſt plot and contrive againſt the Court of <hi>England;</hi> and that all this in the Court hath beene but a defenſive contriving or counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plotting. Nothing more abſurd, nothing more impoſſilbe, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more inconſiſtant with the meanes, nothing more repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to the ends of Parliaments: we muſt ſuppoſe that there are about ten <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> now in Parliament, that firſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:63000:20"/>the major and better part there, and then overcame the major and better part of ſuch as remaine unexpelled; then by authority of <hi>Parliament,</hi> and the help of ſome few other <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts</hi> in the City, they maſter and inſlave the major and bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter part alſo by far, and then by ſome tumults there raiſed, they drive the King and all his popiſh prelaticall courtly and mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie Adherents from the Citie; then they impoſe taxes upon the Kingdome, for the maintaining of divers Armies, and thereby tyrannize as the <hi>Decemviri</hi> did in Rome, in ſpite of King, in ſpite of Nobilitie, in ſpite of Gentrie, in ſpite of Commonaltie, in ſpite of <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> in ſpite of <hi>Papists,</hi> in ſpite of their owne Armies. And then not being ſufficiently diſconſonant to reaſon and nature, we muſt ſuppoſe that theſe ten Anabaptiſts have been in travaile with this deſigne almoſt 40 yeeres before King <hi>Iames</hi> began to comply with <hi>Prelates</hi> and <hi>Papists,</hi> and before <hi>Prelates</hi> and <hi>Papiſts</hi> began to conſpire againſt <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> under the names of <hi>Puritans,</hi> theſe Anabaptiſts were conſulting in a cloſe <hi>Iunto,</hi> how to get themſelves choſen of a <hi>Parliament,</hi> then how to get a <hi>Parliament</hi> call'd, then how to preſerve that <hi>Parliament</hi> from being ever diſſolv'd, then how to effect all theſe divine miracles, by ſuch meanes as none but themſelves ſhould ever be able to diſcerne or comprehend. Is not this a rare ſubject for our great wits at Coutt to work into Proclamations and Declarations? 'Tis reported that the Lord <hi>Digby</hi> of late, being at Mr. <hi>Knightley's</hi> houſe in Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thampton-ſhire in a parlour there, whilſt his Souldiers were buſily ſearching, and plundring, and rifling other roomes, hee ſmote his hand upon the table, and ſwore; That that was the table whereat all theſe civill wars had been plotted at leaſt a dozen yeares before. It ſhould ſeeme Mr. <hi>Pym</hi> had ſojourned ſometime in that houſe and that was ſufficient for an inference, that the neſt of Anabaptiſts had been there too, and that that neſt had ſtudied ſomething, which neither our Kings Cabinet Councellours, nor the <hi>Iunto's</hi> of Italy or Spaine could make defeiſable. But if there were ſome meanes for <hi>Parliaments</hi> thus
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:63000:21"/>to debaſe <hi>Prerogative,</hi> and diſable <hi>Monarchy.</hi> To what end ſhould they attempt it? Is it for the felicitie of <hi>Parliaments,</hi> to ſubject themſelves to ten unlimitable Anabaptiſts, rather than to endure one moſt admirably bounded <hi>Prince,</hi> and rather to make the whole Land a ſtage of bloud, horrout, and cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, than to be preſidented by the loyaltie, policie, and religion of their Anceſtours? Other men have ſpoken and written of this ſufficiently. And beſides, if it were poſſible, if it were profitable for <hi>Parliaments</hi> to turne publike oppreſſours, yet ſenſe and experience tels us, that this <hi>Parliament</hi> hath not uſed any oppreſſion, but with much difficultie been redeemed from oppreſſion. But of this ſufficiently alſo hath been written and ſpoken.</p>
            <p>It remaines therefore, that we compare the means, the ends, the practices of Parliaments, with thoſe of Princes, Papiſts, Prelates, &amp;c. and taking a view of what hath been already ſet forth in this Diſcourſe, parallel the ſame with that which is objected by the other ſide, and it cannot be denyed, but pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates and papiſts have been formerly conſpirers and drawers on of the Scotch war, and other alterations in Church and State, as is here diſcovered. Then the queſtion is, whether or no they have ſince deſiſted, or changed their reſolutions: ſome change perhaps there is, but not ſuch as may ſecure us; for before they did combat againſt us <hi>de victoria,</hi> now <hi>de vita;</hi> hope of victorie before inflamed them, but feare of ruine now exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperates them; and in this reſpect our danger is not the leſſe, but the more.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
